Sometimes we want to do a little more
than just print out a name. So maybe we
want to welcome them to um the welcome
them to the system. So we're going to
say welcome to the system Wanda. Welcome
to the system Pietro. Well, let's do a
little more processing. And maybe we
want to capitalize their entire name. So
inside of our loop, we want to grab
their name. So we'll say let first name
equal and then we'll access the first
names array and we'll access a specific
item in the array and we want to access
whichever one we're currently at.
And then we want to say first name
equals first name dot
two uppercase. That'll make their entire
name uppercase. So, we'll say, let's put
a comment. Say, grab the name,
make the name uppercase.
And you may have noticed I already made
a mistake here. I need square braces
because I need to say I'm not trying to
um Oh, sorry. I want to say take the
first name and make it uppercase. Um,
so grab the first name, store it in a
variable, make it uppercase, store back
in itself, and then now we'll just
welcome to the system. So we'll say
console.log,
welcome to the system
plus, and then we'll concatenate on
first name.
So we'll save this. And
if we go over to our code, we can see it
says, "Welcome to the system, Anna,
Mark, Steven, Jake, Johnny, Danny,
Robbie, Camala, or Carol, Jennifer, and
Norin." Um, and so it looks like it
successfully welcomed them to the
system.
Um, but this can be kind of annoying to
reference items in the array by saying
go to the array and then use square
braces. Whoops. And then do the counter.
And because we do this so often, we loop
through arrays so often, we've actually
made a much easier way to do it. And so
I'm going to show you that easier way.
You can say for and then you create a
new variable name. We'll say let name
of
and then what are you looping through
first names
and then you can console.log log
um welcome to the system
plus
name
dot to
uppercase. So what this does is it says
go find the array then take an item out
of the array and store it in name. Once
you've done that, log it. Then go back
in, grab the next name in the array,
store it in array. Once you've done it,
log it. This loop is doing the exact
same thing as the loop above. The loop
above, I said create a variable called
first name, take an item out of the
loop, and store it. But rather than
writing out the really long syntax and
figuring out the length of the array and
writing the incrementer and all of that
which takes longer to type um and then
going into the array and grabbing
something at whatever the incrementor is
at or counter variable rather than doing
all of that they just said how about you
just make a variable pull something out
of the list and put it in that variable.
Well let's just go see this in action so
you can see that they work very very
similarly. So,
we'll come over to Safari and we're
going to come here to the sources tab
and we're going to put a breakpoint on
line 47.
Um,
oh, and I may need to reload this.
One moment.
Cancel. Reload the page. And it looks
like my for loop has not shown up. Did I
save my code? I did not save my code. Oh
boy. Okay. save the code then go over
and then now you can see the for loop is
here. So there's the for loop and then
below it we call this a for loop. So
right now we're on line 47. We're about
to start the variable. So we grab our
counter. Our counter is zero. Um we run
it for the full length of first
names.length which is 32. We hit next
and then it says first name equals first
names at the counter position. So if we
hit next and we hover over first name,
first name is Peter. So now we're going
to make first name uppercase. Now first
name is uppercase Peter. And now we're
going to log it to the console. If we
come over here to console, it says
welcome to the system Peter. Um then we
run it again and we're about to
increment the counter. So if we
increment the counter now counter is
one.
and one is still less than the length of
32. Um, so we're going to hit next.
We'll drop in here and we'll grab first
name. First name is now Tony. And that's
because we went into the first names
array. We went to the one position and
we grabbed Tony. And then we stored in a
variable called first name.
Then we uppercase that. So now we get
uppercase Tony. And then we print
welcome to the system. So if we come
over here, we get welcome to the system
Peter. Welcome to the system, Tony. Um,
and then we increment, and for good
measure, I'm going to do this one more
time. So, we increment the counter.
Counter is at two. First names, um, has
a length of 32. So, this loop is going
to run again. So, we hit next. We go to
first names at the two position, which
is Steve. And if we hit next, now first
name is holding Steve.
And then we uppercase it. And then we
print it. Now, if we come to the
console, it says, "Welcome to the
system, Steve." So, hopefully you've got
a good idea of how the for loop works.
Now, we're going to put a breakpoint on
the for of loop. So, I'm going to take
this off, and I'm going to hit continue,
and it's going to have printed out all
the rest of the names. And then we'll
come over here. So, it says let name of
first name. So, it comes to first names.
Notice zero is storing Peter. If we hit
next,
it's about to assign the first value in
first names to name. If we hit next and
we hover over name, now we can see that
the name is Peter. So now we're going to
print welcome to the system Peter.2
uppercase. If we hit next
and we come to our console,
oh sorry, we uppercased it. We hit next.
We come to our console and all the way
down it says welcome to the system Peter
and we come back over to our sources.
Now it's hovering over first name. Right
now name is still storing Peter but as
soon as this line runs it's going to
grab the next name out of the list and
put it into name. So if we hit next now
if we hover over name is storing the
text Tony. And if we hit next and then
log it, we come to the console. Now we
can see welcome to the system Tony.
And now if we look at first names, the
very next name in the list is Steve. So
we should expect that if we run this
loop another time, it's going to take
Steve out and store it in name. So if we
hit next, now if we hover over name, now
it's Steve. So you can see that these
loops are doing the exact same thing,
but this loop down here on line 55 uses
much less code to do the exact same
thing as the loop that runs from line 47
to 53.
And if that is something that you
appreciate, then four of loops might be
for you. Um, depending on the developer,
lots of developers live by four of loops
and other developers don't like them at
all. I like for loops, but I will let
you make that decision. I just want you
to be aware that there are two ways to
loop through arrays. There are actually
a lot of ways to loop through arrays,
but two of them are you can use the for
loop where you write out the full
counter and you write it out for the
length and you use the counter++ or you
can use the for of loop where you just
say for let variable name of your array
and then it just pulls each item out of
the array one at a time. And that
concludes this section on four of loops.
Thanks for watching.